Guide to the Takako Wada Papers TAM.723
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Takako Wada Papers
1942-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wada, Takako, 1921-2016
Wada, Stephanie
TAM.723
7 linear feet in 5 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 small media box.
5 audiocassettes
Takako "Taxi" Wada (née Kusunoki) was a writer, editor, and activist whose career reflected her commitment to ensuring Asian American civil rights in the United States. In 1981 she closely followed the public hearings held by the Commission for Wartime Relocation and Internment Civilians all across the country. Materials in this collection include correspondence, testimonies, newsletters, event ephemera, newspapers and newspaper clippings, and other research materials, much of which focuses on the incarceration of Japanese Americans in the United States during World War II and the movement to obtain redress. Files include correspondence (much between Wado and William Hohri, lead plantiff in the National Council for Japanese American Redress lawsuit seeking reparations for incarceration), personal statements and testimonies submitted to Wada for the public hearing held in New York City on November 23, 1981, as well as transcripts of the hearing. In addition to materials concerning incarceration and redress, the collection includes materials documenting Wada's journalism career, her work with JASSI (Japanese American Social Services), newsletters and other materials for Asian American civil rights activism, and ephemera for Asian American cultural and community events.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Stephanie Wada in 2017 and 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gift are 2018.076 and 2019.085.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Takako "Taxi" Wada (née Kusunoki) (1921-2016) was a writer, editor, and activist whose career reflected her commitment to ensuring Asian American civil rights in the United States. Born in Colusa, California, Takako was incarcerated with her mother and two sisters at the Granada War Relocation Center ("Camp Amache") in Colorado in 1942. As a young adult she spent two years in the Women's Army Corps, worked as a journalist and, studied painting in the studio of Fernand Ledger in Paris on the G.I. Bill of Rights. She was an active supporter of the redress for Japanese Americans who were incarcerated during World War II. In 1981 she closely followed the public hearings held by the Commission for Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians all across the country. During this time Takako collected testimonies, conducted research, and edited personal statements all pertaining to the hearings, with particular attention paid to those held in Washington D.C., New York, and California. Serving as the English editor for the Japanese American newspaper New York Nicibei, Takako nurtured and supported topics concerning Asian American rights, women's rights, community service, and arts movements.
Scope and Contents
The Takako Wada Papers (dated 1945-2004) consist of materials created and collected by Wado documenting her journalism and activism for Japanese Americans and the broader Asian American civil rights movement. Materials in this collection include correspondence, testimonies, newsletters, event ephemera, newspapers and newspaper clippings, and other research materials. Many of the materials in the collection pertain to the incarceration of Japanese Americans in the United States during World War II, with specific emphasis on the movement to obtain redress and the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians public hearings. Files include correspondence (much between Wado and William Hohri, lead plantiff in the National Council for Japanese American Redress lawsuit seeking reparations for incarceration), personal statements and testimonies submitted to Wada in her capacity as English editor of New York Nichibei, a newspaper published by the Japanese American News Corporation, for the public hearing held in New York City on November 23, 1981 as well as transcripts of the hearing. Additional legal transcripts that make up the collection pertain to other hearings held in Washington, D.C. on July 14 and 16, 1981; Cambridge, Massachusetts on December 9, 1981; Los Angeles, California August 4-6, 1981; and Alaska on September 15, 17, and 19, 1981. The witnesses include people who were incarcerated, government officials who ran and supported the mass forced removal and incarceration program, and organizations such as the Japanese American Citizens League and American Friends Service Committee. In addition to materials concerning incarceration and redress, the collection includes materials documenting Wada's journalism career, her work with JASSI (Japanese American Social Services), newsletters and other materials for Asian American civil rights activism, ephemera for Asian American cultural and community events, and issues of Japanese American newspapers or magazines, including Asahi Evening News, Bandwagon, Gidra, Getting Together, and New York Nichibei.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Japanese Americans -- History -- 20th century.; Japanese Americans -- Reparations.; Testimonies.; Public hearings.; New York (N.Y.).; Japanese American newspapers.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese Americans -- Social conditions.; United States. Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians; Wada, Stephanie; Japanese American Social Services, Inc.
- Wada, Takako: Personal Notebook, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- New York Nichibei: Statements Submitted to Wada, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
- Massachusetts: Statement and Agenda for Cambridge Public Hearing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Public Law 96-317, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Washington, D.C.: Testimony by American Friends Service Company, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- News Clips from The Rafu Shimpo, Los Angeles Japanese Daily News, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Washington, D.C.: Department of State Testimony, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- News Article from the Denver Post, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- News Clips from the Rafu Shimpo, Los Angeles Japanese Daily News, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Suzuki, Peter T., Ph.D.: Statement Submitted to Commission, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Washington, D.C.: Statements to the Commission, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- East Coast Japanese Americans for Redress, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- ABC News: Transcript for Washington, D.C. Hearing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Newspaper for The Hokubei Shimps, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Statements for the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- National Council for Japanese American Redress, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Japanese American Citizens League, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Research Materials, 1942, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Washington, D.C.: Statement of Joan Z. Bernstein, Chair of Commission, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Research Materials concerning Concentration Camps during World War II, 1940-1943, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Washington, D.C.: Statement of Joan Z. Bernstein, Chair of Commission and Other Materials, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Research Materials concerning U.S. Government and Concentration Camps, 1942-1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians: Statement of Mike M. Masaoka, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- New York City: Statements for New York Public Hearing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- New York City: Statements, Testimonies, and Agenda for Public Hearing in New York, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Japanese American Citizens League, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- New York City: The New York Hearing by the Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians: Press Kit, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Research Materials concerning Prisoner at Concentration Camp, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Wada, Takako: Miscellaneous Notes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- News Clippings about Public Hearings Held by Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Research Materials concerning Japanese-Americans and WWII Incarceration, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- News Articles (Copies), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Asian American Legal Defense and Education Fund: Statements, Transcript, and Agenda for Public Hearings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Commission on Wartime Relocation and Internment of Civilians: Statement of Mike Masaoka, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Manzanar National Historic Site, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- AALDEF, 1973-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Redress, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Mitzu on Issei, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- W.H. Horhri, the Epistolarian, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Festival Programs, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Isaku Kida, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "Against All Odds: The Japanese Americans' Campaign for Redress", 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Yoshida, Takashi: "Standing Loyally by the Flag: The Experience of People of Japanese Ancestry in New York During World War II" (draft of paper), circa 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Aging, Social Security, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Nichibei Materials, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Japanese American Social Services, Inc. (JASSI), 1983-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
- Correspondence, Ephemera, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
- Correspondence, 1973-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24-29)
- State of New York Authorship Rights, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Chushingura, circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Films, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Young/Chin, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Asian Americans in the Arts, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
- Photographs -- UN Rally, Hiroshima, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Photographs -- Genera, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Photographs -- "Pacific Overtures", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Correspondence, 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Programs, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Publications, 1945-1993 (Box 2, Folder 44-45, Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs -- General, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Daisho Miyagawa, 1981-1992 (Box 3, Folder 3-8)
- William Hohri, 1994-2004 (Box 3, Folder 9-15)
- Memorial Services, 1990-2001 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
- Films, 1962-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
- Miné Okubo, 1972-2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Japanese American News Corp. Stationary, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1963-2000 (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
- Calendars, 1990, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Japanese American Social Services, Inc. (JASSI), 1986-2005 (Box 3, Folder 26-31)
- Consumer Guide to NYC Hospitals, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Newsletters and Magazines, 1998-2005 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Pacific Citizen, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 34, Box Shared Tamiment 057, Folder 2)
- Daily News, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Rodan, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Getting Together, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Gidra, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Conversations with Eric Sevareid, John J. McCoy, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Basement Workshop Yearbook, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Japanese American Social Services, Inc. (JASSI) Newsletters, 1993-2003 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Asian American Films, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Photographs -- General, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1966, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Miné Okubo, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Karl Yoneda, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Arizona, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Michi Weglyn, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- The New York Nichibei, 1967, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 18-20)
- National Japanese American Memorial Foundation, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Bandwagon, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
- Santa Anita Pacemaker, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- William Hohri, 1983-2004 (Box 4, Folder 26-29)
- National Council for Japanese American Redress, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
- Asian Americans for Action, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 32-34)
- The New York Nichibei, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Gidra, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- The Hokubi Shimpo, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Asahi Evening News, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- New York Times, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Raymond Okamura, Iva Toguri ("Tokyo Rose"), 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
- Asian Americans for Action, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1980, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Miné Okubo, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Manzanar, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Miwa Yanamoto Newsletter, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- World War II Veterans, 1985-1995 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Films, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Isaku and Emi Kida, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 49)
- World War II Veterans, 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Asian Americans for Action, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2-6)
- Films, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Day of Remembrance, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Programs, Ephemera, 1976-1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1990-2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Newspaper Clippings, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Miné Okubo, 1978-2000 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
- T-shirts, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
- Gidra, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Population Maps, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Audio cassette: Richard McGeorge, 1979-03-14 (Box 7)
- Audio cassette: Dennis Roland (I), 1979-01-11 (Box 7)
- Audio cassette: Dennis Roland (II), 1979-01-11 (Box 7)
- Audio cassette: 60 Minutes -- Koramatsu Case, 1984-02-19 (Box 7)
- Audio cassette: B. Dalton Pickwick Commercial for "Years of Infamy"; Barry Farber Show, WOR NY Interview; Michi Weglyn Interview, undated (Box 7)
- Vase, undated (Box 7)